I've covered fasting as a form of
intervention against cancer before, but
the reality is that in a clinical sense,
there just isn't that much data. So,
it's not like there are many studies
that we can then point to and say, "Yes,
definitely fasting helps fight off
cancer." And I think one of the barriers
is the length of many fasts. Now,
typically for more involved fasting,
we're talking about a full day or more,
but all of that may be changing because
a recent study used a mixture of animal
and human experiments, including a small
clinical study to assess if more
manageable fasting that lasts less than
a day can have potent anti-cancer
effects, like what I'll be explaining
related to this image of a person with
cancer regression Here, for example,
intermittent fasting led to an increase
in anti-cancer signatures within immune
cells shown in the blue violin plot. In
the less science speak, that means that
intermittent fasting increased the
number of proteins and behaviors by
immune cells that are consistent with
being aggressive toward cancer. And it
reduces the number of proteins produced
that inhibit anti-cancer behavior. Now,
I'm not going to bore you with all the
data, but this was confirmed across
multiple other measures like immune cell
exhaustion, uh, where immune cells are
inhibited from attacking cancer and
more. Well, one more for good measure
because I think it's just such a cool
image and it tells a cool story. The
little bright dots in the images are
individual cells and as they're grouped
together, they are more similar in their
gene expression. Meaning that the more
of the same genes are being read and
ultimately produced into proteins. That
white circle there is identifying a key
population of cells unique to fasting.
See how the control the non-fasting
condition is missing that group compared
to the fasting? Well, that's because it
doesn't have them like fasting promotes.
So, why does that matter? Uh, are you
kidding me? Do you not know who these
cells are? They're like the delta force
of immune cells. I'm dying to get their
autograph. Anyway, they're called Terra,
which is an even more specialized form
of T- cell, a powerful anti-cancer cell.
The big picture here is that
intermittent fasting changes the body to
be primed against cancer. Still, there's
bigger and better things to cover
because this study, as I mentioned, was
in a mixture of human and mouse
research. And some of the data that we
went over was in mice. Let me ask you,
do you think that fasting a mouse for a
period of the day is the same as a
person fasting for the same length of
time? The answer is no. So, how can we
even trust the mouse data to be even
remotely representative of humans? Well,
we can't innately unless we test it
directly. And the researchers did the
same experiment in mice as they did in
humans, comparing a profile of cancer
related molecules between different
fasting periods shown here. Now they're
grouping the overall results into these
little circles with the purple at the
bottom being the unfasted mice and the
unfasted humans. Then by direction, 12
hours of fasting leads to some changes
in these cancer related molecules
relative to the unfasted conditions
because the teal color are in a
different spot in the graph and then
everything shifts over with the 16 hours
of fasting. The point here isn't to
understand what all this means, but to
simply recognize that there's a very
similar pattern between mice and humans
when comparing non-fasted versus 16
hours of fasting. This doesn't prove
that humans are just like mice or vice
versa, but it provides some evidence
that in the context that we're
discussing, there's similarity. So that
means that the title of the study is not
just some random number of hours fasting
beyond the common nature of 16-hour
fasts, but that 16 hours of fasting,
even in humans, leads to changes in
molecules produced in the body related
to cancer that are not produced with
shorter fasting. And in fact, remember
these data? I didn't mention it, but
that's in humans with colctal cancer. So
they were able to show intermittent
fasting has an effect on the immune
system as well, not just changes in
cancer related molecules. The point
being 16 hours of fasting is the number
to implement. Actually, we aren't
limited to immune changes either. Next,
I'd like to get into some more
impressive human evidence and add some
context to this all. But if you're
looking for more depth into how
intermittent fasting manipulates cancer
cells into a deadly exchange of amino
acids or how intermittent fasting may
have a unique effects on cancer cells
not shared by immune cells or even more
on the mighty Terra cells, then check
out the full version of this video that
you're watching. It's an extended
analysis including an article, a one
paragraph summary of all the most
important points and more. Plus, you get
all these perks right over here, Sunny.
Access to it all is through becoming a
Physionic Insider. The link to join is
in the description. I hope to see you
there. Allow me to introduce you to
these CT scans in people using
intermittent fasting on the bottom and
those not up top. The red circles
identify the cancer location. So you'll
notice that the person who was
intermittent fasting experienced a
reduction in tumor size that was not
present for those not fasting. Now
remarkable especially for such a simple
fasting protocol and when repeated
across small groups of people with
colctal cancer. The red is before and
the blue dots are after. We're measuring
tumor size. Those not fasting did not
experience any average change, but those
that did fast experienced significant
reductions in tumor size. So this all
means that in preclinical and early
clinical research, intermittent fasting
for 16 hours paired with imunotherapy
beats back cancer tumors not seen in
identical scenarios missing fasting. As
always, this stuff will be context
dependent like the type of cancer, the
stage of cancer, and more. But it's one
of the very few studies to actually show
intermittent fasting isn't just a weight
loss technique, but can impact the body
in wonderful ways that are beginning to
extend into the cancer realm. That's for
exciting times. But here's the thing.
Yes, not many studies on fasting except
I cover a more wellstudied form of
fasting that has stronger clinical
evidence against cancer right here. I'll
catch you over there. Thanks for tuning
in. It's always appreciated. And I hope
that you learned something of value.
I'll see you in the next one.